Finding Aid for Philip Kerr papers, 1984-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip Kerr papers 1984-2012
Kerr, Philip.
2012093 Aa 2
Philip Kerr, a professional actor, taught theatre at the University of Michigan from 1984 to 2012. In addition to teaching courses in the Department of Theatre and Drama, he directed many productions put on by the department. This collection includes material documenting these productions and his role as a faculty member.
1.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Philip Kerr (donor no 10779 ) in 2012.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Philip Kerr was born April 9, 1940, in New York City. He attended secondary school at Westminster School in Simsbury, Connecticut, graduating in 1959. He then attended Harvard College, where he was a member of the Harvard Dramatic Club and won awards such as the McCord Prize for Artistic Achievement and the Leveritt House Art Prize. He graduated from Harvard in 1963. Following his time at Harvard, Kerr completed a one-year advanced course at the London Academy of Music and Dramatic Art.
In the next twenty years, Kerr's activities included teaching master classes in advanced scene study at the American Conservatory Theatre in San Francisco, Indiana State University, and the College of the Sequoias; serving as lecturer at the University of California at Santa Barbara and Webster College Conservatory and Visiting Professor of Theatre at Bennington College; and acting on Broadway as well as with off-Broadway institutions such as the Manhattan Theatre Club, Roundabout Theatre, and CSC Repertory Theatre.
Kerr joined the University of Michigan Department of Theatre and Drama faculty in 1984. In addition to teaching acting courses and directing productions, he was instrumental in the establishment of the Bachelor of Fine Arts program. In 1994, he was appointed Claribel Baird Halstead Collegiate Professor of Theatre. Professor Kerr retired in 2012. He was a member of many professional associations, such as the Actors' Equity Association, Screen Actors' Guild, Society of Stage Directors and Choreographers, Society of American Fight Directors, and Dramatists' Guild.
The Philip Kerr Papers document Kerr's time at the University of Michigan as a professor in the Department of Theatre and Drama. They primarily contain records and publications from productions in which Kerr was director or an actor, as well as administrative records reflecting Kerr's role and experiences as a faculty member within the Department of Theatre and Drama, especially his efforts to improve the quality of the department, such as the establishment of the Bachelor in Fine Arts degree program. The collection is arranged into five series: Biographical, Correspondence, Photographs, Productions, and Topical.
Subjects:
Kerr, Philip.; Actors.; College theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Theater--Production and direction.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Music, Theatre & Dance.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series includes articles from American Theatre and TheaterWeek publications containing material on Kerr. Also included in this series is Kerr's Curriculum Vitae.
  - Articles (Box 1)
    - American Theatre, 1990 (Box 1)
      (photo on page 19)
    - TheaterWeek, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Curricula Vitae, circa 2000, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains correspondence between Kerr and fellow faculty members within the Department of Theatre and Drama.
  - Arnold Aronson 1988 (Box 1)
  - Benedict Nightingale 1987 (Box 1)
  - General 1985-2010 (Box 1)
  - John Russell Brown 1985-1986 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains photos of Kerr, his students, and productions with which he was involved. Note that some additional photographs are located in the files of particular theatrical productions.
  - Philip Kerr undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
- Productions
  The Productions series includes material on productions in which Kerr served, mostly as director, but also a few in which he was an actor. It is therefore divided into two subseries, Actor and Director. Most of the productions Kerr directed were put on by the Department of Theatre and Drama. Material contained in this series includes programs, flyers, costume and set design sketches, photos, and planning documents for the productions.
  - Actor
    - A Christmas Carol
      - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - 1993 (Box 1)
      - 1994 (Box 1)
    - Romeo and Juliet 2005 (Box 1)
  - Director
    - 8 2012 (Box 1)
    - Arms and the Man 2011 (Box 1)
    - As You Like It 1984 (Box 1)
    - The Baltimore Waltz 1993 (Box 1)
    - The Best People 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Born Guilty 1997 (Box 1)
      (includes photos)
    - The Crucible 1999 (Box 1)
    - The Dining Room 1985 (Box 1)
    - Dogg's Hamlet, Cahoot's Macbeth 1983 (Box 1)
    - A Doll's House 1985 (Box 1)
    - Endgame 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Ghosts 1996 (Box 1)
    - The Glass Menagrie 1994 (Box 1)
    - The Gold Diggers 2006 (Box 1)
    - Hamlet 2002 (Box 1)
    - The Heiress 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - J.B. 2007 (Box 1)
    - Julius Caesar 2001 (Box 1)
    - Lysistrata 1985 (Box 1)
    - Macbeth 2009 (Box 1)
    - A Midsummer Night's Dream
      - 1997-1998 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
        (includes photo)
    - Our Town 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Present Laughter 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Private Lives 1993 (Box 1)
    - Quick Change Room 2002-2004 (Box 1)
    - Romeo and Juliet 2005 (Box 1)
    - The Show-Off 2009 (Box 1)
    - The Skin of Our Teeth 1987 (Box 1)
    - Some Enchanted Evening 1988 (Box 1)
    - Suddenly Last Summer 2011 (Box 1)
    - The Taming of the Shrew 1986 (Box 1)
    - The Tavern 2002 (Box 1)
    - Tartuffe 1990 (Box 1)
    - The Tempest
      - 1999 (Box 1)
      - 2000 (Box 1)
    - Twelfth Night 1995 (Box 1)
- Topical
  The Topical series contains material documenting a variety of Kerr's activities. These include his leadership role in the creation of the Bachelor of Fine Arts program, appointment as Claribel Baird Halstead Collegiate Professor of Theatre, commencement speech at the December 1996 School of Music commencement, involvement with the Ensemble Theatre Company, and sabbatical activities, among others.
  - Bachelor of Fine Arts Program (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1988-1992 (Box 2)
    - Documents 1989-2003, undated (Box 2)
  - Bachelor of Theatre Arts Degree 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Claribel Baird Halstead Collegiate Professor of Theatre Appointment 1994-2001 (Box 2)
  - Commencement Speech 1996 (Box 2)
  - Employment Status Notifications 1984-2010 (Box 2)
  - Ensemble Theatre Company undated (Box 2)
  - Essay: "The Politician as Actor," 1981 (Box 2)
    (printed in Politics, Power, and Shakespeare, Texas Humanities Resource Center)
  - Faculty Activities Reports 1984-2005 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Praise 1985-2003 (Box 2)
  - Master of Fine Arts Program in Acting 1984, undated (Box 2)
  - Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association Certification 1995 (Box 2)
  - Outstanding Faculty Achievements Award 1989 (Box 2)
  - Preparing the Acting Teacher: Shakespeare Workshop 1989 (Box 2)
  - Promotion Review 1991 (Box 2)
  - Sabbatical
    - 1992 (Box 2)
    - 2000 (Box 2)
    - 2006 (Box 2)
  - Search Committee 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Teaching/Production Proposal 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Theatre Department Planning 1988-2011 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Concentration in Theatre and Drama; Recommendations by Benedict Nightingale 1986 (Box 2)